Guide to the Gil Green Papers TAM 095
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Gil Green Papers
Bulk, 1972-1991
1949-1993, (Bulk 1972-1991)
TAM 095
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
14.75 linear feet (19 boxes)
Gil Green (1906-1997) was a Communist, a Smith Act defendant, and a prominent figure in the CPUSA through 1991. As a youth, he joined the Young Workers League (later the Young Communist League) eventually becoming its national secretary. From 1941-1945 and again from 1966-1968, Green was head of the Party in New York State and also briefly headed Illinois' Party organization. Convicted under the Smith Act in 1949, Green was impirsoned from 1956 until 1961. He left the Party in 1991 and founded the Committees of Correspondence. These papers include his correspondence, writings, documentation of his political activities, and FBI files regarding their investigation of him. NOTE: this collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for its use.
Green, Gil, 1906-
Box 1-19
Provenance
Gift of Gil Green, c.1980, 1993.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: this collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for its use.
Historical/Biographical Note
Gil Green (1906-1997), born Gilbert Greenberg in Chicago, the son of working class Russian-Jewish immigrants, was a Communist youth leader in the 1930s, a member of the Communist Party's Politburo, a Smith Act defendant, and the chief (albeit unofficial) figure of a reformist current in the CPUSA through 1991. Although high school valedictorian he did not go to college. Instead he joined the Young Workers League (later the Young Communist League) in 1924, and shortly thereafter, the CPUSA. He rose through the ranks, and in 1932 became national secretary of the YCL, a position he held throughout the decade, where he trained a generation of Party cadres and led the League to a position of influence in the 1.7 million member American Youth Congress. In 1935 he attended the Comintern's Seventh Congress, where he was an advocate for the emerging Popular Front policy. In 1941 Green became head of the Party in New York State, but had to relinquish this title in 1945 due to his association with Earl Browder, the ousted Party head, and moved to Illinois, where he headed that state's Party organization. Convicted under the Smith Act in 1949, Green became a fugitive, surrendered in 1956 and was released from jail in 1961. By 1966, Green was again head of the New York Party, but resigned this position in 1968 to protest the CPUSA's endorsement of the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia. He remained an elder statesman and locus of CP reform currents until 1991, when he left the Party and helped to found the Committees of Correspondence, a social-democratic organization. For additional information, see: Biographical Dictionary of the American Left(1986).
Works by Gil Green:
Marxism and the world today. New York: New York State Committee, Communist Party, n.d. 23 p.
Youth confronts the Blue Eagle. New York: Youth Publishers, November, 1933. 29 p.
United we stand: for peace and socialism. New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1935. 63 p.
Young Communists and the unity of youth. Speech delivered at the 7th World Congress of the Communist International. New York: Youth Publishers, October, 1935. 15 p.
Facing the 8th convention of the Young Communist League. Report, delivered Jan. 1, 1937. New York: Young Communist League, n.d.
Make your dreams come true. Report to the 8th national convention of the Young Communist League, New York City, May 2, 1937. New York: Workers Library Publishers, June, 1937. 47 p.
The truth about Soviet Russia. New York: New Age Publishers, March, 1938. 48 p.
America must act now! New York: Workers Library Publishers, November, 1941. 14 p.
New York State's wartime election. New York: New York State Communist Party, September, 1942. 24 p.
Marxism and the world today. New York: New York State Committee, Communist Party, [1944?]. 23 p.
The enemy forgotten. New York, International Publishers [1956]. 318 p.
Revolution Cuban style; impressions of a recent visit. New York, International Publishers [1970]. 125 p.
Terrorism - is it revolutionary? New York: New Outlook Publishers, 1970. 40 p.
The new radicalism: anarchist or Marxist? New York: International Publishers, 1971. 189 p.
What's happening to labor. New York: International Publishers, 1976. 305 p.
Portugal's revolution. New York: International Publishers, 1976. 99 p.
Cuba at 25: the continuing revolution. New York: International Publishers, 1983. 117 p.
Cold war fugitive: a personal story of the McCarthy years. New York: International Publishers, 1984. 275 p.
Scope and Content Note
The General Correspondence (most incoming, arranged alphabetically) is primarily with like-minded communists, ex-communists, other U.S. leftists, historians and other researchers, and is primarily concerned with communist history and with current events, radical thought and activity. There is also some family correspondence. Prominent and/or principal correspondents include: Harry Bridges, Lloyd Brown, David Engelstein, Sender Garlin, Dorothy Healey, Kate Hyndman, Lolita Lebron and other Puerto Rican radicals, Sidney Lens, Helen North (his second wife), Paul Robeson Jr., Bill Schneiderman, Pat Toohey, Saul Wellman and Leon Wofsy. The Addendum to this series consists of additional correspondence with David Englestein and Sender Garlin. The Prison Correspondence, arranged chronologically, consists of copies of (mostly outgoing) letters, most to his first wife (Lil Green, 1910-1964) and children, some to political associates and attorneys. The Political Activities, Associates and Writings series contains unpublished typescripts by Green and others, notably James Allen's memoir Marxist Publishing(n.d., 44 pp.), A Labor Revolutionary in Detroit(re Nat Ganley), and Green's 1968 notes on his remarks on Czechoslovakia at the CP's Central Committee meeting thereon; editorial files pertaining to the writing, publication and reception of several of Green's later books, notably his autobiographical Cold War Fugitive(1984); third party correspondence of several of Green's political friends and associates, notably Lloyd Brown; and a file of Smith Act-related material obtained under the Freedom of Information Act. The last series, FBI Files, were also obtained by Green under the FOIA. NOTE: this collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for its use.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, General; II. Correspondence, General Addendum (0.25 lf); III. Correspondence, Prison; IV. Political Activities, Associates, and Writings; V. FBI Files (12 linear feet, unprocessed).
Folders are arranged alphabetically except series III which is arranged chronologically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Counterattack Research Files (Tamiment 148)
Series 50, file 33 (0.5 lf), is a compilation of documentation on the Illinois Communist Party, 1946-1950,and on Green's leadership thereof, including reportage and analysis by informants and government agents.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Brown, Lloyd L., (Lloyd Louis), 1913-; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Engelstein, David; Garlin, Sender A.; Green, Gil, 1906-; Green, Lil, 1910-1964.; Healey, Dorothy.; Hyndman, Kate.; Lebrón, Lolita, 1919-; Lens, Sidney.; North, Helen.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976.; Schneiderman, William.; Toohey, Pat.; United States. Alien Registration Act, 1940.; Wellman, Saul; Wofsy, Leon.; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Young Workers League of America.; Case files.; Communists |z United States.; Correspondence.; Czechoslovakia--History--Intervention, 1968.; Memoirs.; New York (N.Y.); Radicals--Puerto Rico.; Revolutionaries--Puerto Rico.; Typescripts.
- Series I. Correspondence, General.
  Scope and Contents note
  Location: 1. Cage - B7f, 6 mss. boxes (2.5 lf); 2. Waverley - 3A1-3, 12 Paige boxes (12 lf).
  - Amter, Nell, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aptheker, Bettina, 1971, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bender, Stanley, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boyte, Harry (New American Movement), 1974-1976, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bridges, Harry & Nikki, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Lloyd, 1949-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Buhle, Paul, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Milt, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Engelstein, David & Mary, 1972-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family and Family History, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Garlin, Sender, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Gates?], Johnny: GG "critical response to your Open Letter, Jan 17, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gerson, Si, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gordon, Max, 1983, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Green, Gil: Housing - Racial Discrimination, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Green, Gil: Letters to Editors, 1949, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Healey, Dorothy, ca.1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Historians, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hyndman, Kate, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kalter, Rose - re Dave Doran, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lebron, Lolita, Apr 10, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lens, Sidney, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Liveright, Betty and Herman, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Marquit, Erwin (GG to), Jul 4, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mello, Servio (Brazil), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, ca.1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Navasky, Victor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - North, Helen, 1966-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pajetta, Giuliano (PCI member of Parliament), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Peck, Sid, 1960, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Puerto Rico - correspondence & FOIA documents, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Richmond, Al, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5A)
  - Robeson, Paul Jr. - GG ltr to, Apr 14, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5B)
  - Rubin, Danny and Maurice [Spector?], 1985, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sandy, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Schendel, Herman, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Schneiderman, Bill, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sennett, William, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Toohey, Pat, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wellman, Saul, 1977-1978, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Whitman, Alden, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wofsy, Leon, 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - General - Addendum
    - Englestein, David - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    - Englestein, David - Political-Ideological Letters to GG, 1981-1987 (Box 2A, Folder 2)
    - Garlin, Sender - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 2A, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Prison.
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Feb 1956-Apr 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, May 1956-Dec 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series III. Correspondence, Prison.
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series IV. Projects, Activities, Associates, Topics
  - Allen, James - Marxist Publishing(memoir, 44 p. ts), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Lloyd - Correspondence with others, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Lloyd - Letters to the Editor (New York Times), 1959-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chancey, Martin - The American Left in Disarray(ts, 20 p.), ca. late 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chile - Overthrow of Allende, undated (Box 5, Folder 4A)
  - Foster, notes on - by Arthur Zipser, undated (Box 5, Folder 4B)
  - Ganley, Ann - Reminiscences, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ganley, Nat: A Labor Revolutionary in Detroit - a Biographical Monograph by Michael Devereaux Whitty. 22 p., undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ganley, Nat: Writings - published and unpublished, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Green, Gil: An Aesopian Letter, ca.1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Green, Gil: Aristocracy of Labor, for Commission on, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Green, Gil: Contradictions in Developing Socialism (Berkeley - Marxist Scholars Conference), Nov 14, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Green, Gil: Cold War Fugitive- correspondence, reviews, etc., ca.1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Green, Gil: Contradictions in Developing Socialism. Berkeley, CA, Marxist Scholars Conference, Nov 14, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Green, Gil: Cuba at Twenty-Five: the Continuing Revolution correspondence, publicity, reviews, etc., 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Green, Gil: "Curriculum" (for a proposed Marxist school), ca.1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Green, Gil: Czechoslovakia - "Notes on my remarks in Central Committee discussion...", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Green, Gil: Democracy, the Key to Party Growth, ca.1990 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Green, Gil: If Justice Murphy Took the Stand, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Green, Gil: Reflections on Gus Hall's article, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Green, Gil: Report - New York State CP Committee Meeting, Jan 28, 1965-Jan 29, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Green, Gil: Smith Act-related FOIA documents & correspondence, 1948-1984 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Green, Gil: Summary of Four Lectures on Glasnost. Berkshire Forum, Jul 24, 1987-Jul 26, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Green, Gil: "U.S.A." - lesson plans, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Green, Gil: Thompson, Robert - Remarks at His Re-Burial at Arlington National Cemetery, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Green, Gil: "U.S.A." - Lesson Plans, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Green, Gil: What's Happening to Labor- correspondence, reviews, etc., ca.1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Green, Gil: Writings, Miscellaneous & Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Green, Lil: In Memoriam, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hall, Gus (re): Reply to the Gus Hall Slander (Japanese CP), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Harrington, Michael - research file, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Jacques, Jeffrey: "What is Socialism?", 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Myerson, Michael - U.S. Peace Council 10th Anniversary, Nov 10, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Two Songs for the Exiles (to Gil Green and Henry Winston), undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series V. FBI Files. (Unprocessed)
  - FBI Files. (Unprocessed), undated (Box 7-18)